Guide to the Bureau of Police Station #7 (South Side) and #9 (Mt. Washington), Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1939-1962 AIS.1983.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bureau of Police Station #7 (South Side) and #9 (Mt. Washington), Pittsburgh, Pa., Records
1939-1962
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh (Pa.). Bureau of Police
AIS.1983.01
19 microfilm_reels (plus 7 manuscript cases)
Records of Pittsburgh Police Station #7 (South Side) and #9 (Mt. Washington) which include magistrate's report, daily records, complaint books, magistrates dockets, offense reports, juvenile court case referrals, juvenile court motor vehicle violations, officer personnel cards, employee report of industrial injury, and officer's and physician's reports for motor vehicle operators from 1939-1962.
Related Material
The researcher may also wish to consult the records (1896-1935) of the Pittsburgh, Pa., Bureau of Police (AIS.1972.11). That collection contains general orders, arrest dockets, complaint reports, reports of investigations and arrests, prisoner receipt books, duty roster, correspondence and criminal photo album for the #4 (Oakland) and the #10 (Hazelwood) district police stations.
Scope and Content Notes
The records (1939-1962) of the Pittsburgh Bureau of Police, Station Number 7 (South Side) and State Number 9 (Mt. Washington) document the daily activities of its operation. Part of the records are on microfilm.
The records include: magistrates dockets, 1940-1957; daily records, 1956-1962; inspector's reports, 1949-1958; employer reports of industrial injury, 1950-1958; officer's and physician's reports for motor vehicle operators, 1955-1958; offense reports, 1955-1956; supplement to offense reports, 1955-1956; juvenile court case referrals, 1955-1958; juvenile court motor vehicle violations, 1958; officer's personnel cards; and complaint books, 1939-1959.
The records provide a glimpse of what was happening on the South Side and Mt. Washington for the period 1939-1962 as far as the police were concerened. The complaint books, offense reports (1955-1956), juvenile court case referrals (1955-1958), juvenile court motor vehicle violations (1958), and officer's and physician's reports for motor vehicle operators (1955-1958) detail the crime that took place in a mostly blue collar community. Reports of domestic violence, strikes, burglaries and robberies, child abuse, drunken driving, runaways are all here. Particularly useful for this topic are the juvenile court case referrals, offense reports, and the physician's reports for vehicle operators. In addition to the circumstances of the crime or accident, information about the victim's or suspect's parents, home life or habits (for juvenile cases), occupation, race, sex, age, home addresses, and the makes of vehicles are recorded. Because of their relative recency, the juvenile court case referrals and the juvenile court motor vehicle violations are restricted for 75 years from date of creation; access can be granted by signing a confidentiality agreement.
Employer reports of industrial injury and officer's personnel cards give the individual officer's name, race, age, sex, rank, home address, wages per month, week or day, days worked, languages spoken, how hurt, and how long off the job. Perhaps the most useful of these records for documenting an individual officer are the officer's personnel cards. Most of the cards, which are arranged alphabetically, contain the officer's former occupation, dates and place of birth, rank, date for next promotion, languages spoken, type of gun, address, ward, and district. Included, too, are the types of equipment issued and the inspection of such equipment.
History
The Pittsburgh Bureau of Police began in 1794 when the Borough of Pittsburgh was incorporated. Under the act of 1794, a High Constable and a night watch were provided for the borough. An Act of 1804 (November 5, 1804, P.L. 199) was created which placed constables and the night watch directly under the mayor's control. (At this time, city government was established with a bicameral council and the mayor's court.)
The Director of Public Safety was, in 1888, under the Select and Common Council. Under the Department of Public Safety were included the Bureaus of: Police, Fire, Electricity, Health, Building, Inspectors, Plumbing Inspectors, City Gauger, Police Telegraph, and Garbage Furnace. In 1901, an executive department was provided (March 7, 1901, P.L. 20) and the Department of Public Safety was included. At the same time, the mayor was responsible for appointing the Director of Public Safety. The Director, in 1901, managed the police, public health, fire, fire alarm telegraph, creation of fire escapes, inspection of buildings and boilers, markets and food, and the construction, protection and repair of buildings erected for police purposes.
Later, the Director's responsibilities were limited. The director supervises the different bureaus, the heads of which are responsible to her/him. Under the Director is a general office which coordinates the different bureaus. These are presently, fire; electricity, building inspection, traffic planning, and police.
The Superintendent of Police is appointed by the Director of Public Safety. The superintendent is responsible for the divisions of the Bureau of Police which are: the Office of the Assistant Superintendent, Traffic, Foot and Radio Patrol, and Detectives.
Station Number 7 is located at 93 S. 13th Street in District 5 on the South Side of Pittsburgh. The South Side Magistrate's office is located in Station #7. In 1959, the City of Pittsburgh re-organized the Bureau of Police and several stations were assigned new numbers; Station #7 retained its original designation.
This history of the Pittsburgh Bureau of Police, South Side, Station Number 7 has been compiled from: Clarence Barclay Duncan, "The Evolution of the Government of Pittsburgh" (M.A. Thesis, University of Pittsburgh, 1929); William G. Willis, The Pittsburgh Manual (Pittsburgh, Pa.: University of Pittsburgh), 92-97; Pittsburgh Post-Gazette 14 January 1952; and ibid. 13 August 1960.
Acquisition Information
Records donated by Howard Eisner of Pittsburgh, Pa., January 1983.
Access Restrictions
The following records are closed for 75 years from date of creation: Juvenile Court Case Referrals and the Juvenile Court Motor Vehicle Violations. Permission to use these records can be gained by signing a confidneitality agreement.
Previous Citation
Bureau of Police Station #7 (South Side) and #9 (Mt. Washington), Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1939-1962, AIS.1983.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
South Side (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Mount Washington (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Juvenile courts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Government; Crime -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Police -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Police stations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Police reports -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social conditions; Justices of the peace -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Criminals -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Juvenile delinquency -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Police magistrates -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.). Bureau of Police; Pittsburgh (Pa.). Department of Public Safety
- Inspector's Reports, 1949-1958; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Records of daily activities and investigations. Reports on arrests, investigations of break-ins, strike details at Gimbel's warehouse, gambling house raids. Assignment of beats are listed along with the daily report of river boat personnel, the inspection of motor vehicles on A.M. turn. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Daily Records, 1956-1962; II.
  Log book of police activities at Station #7. A record of the daily/nightly activities of the police station. Records officers' names, ranks, jobs assigned or hours to be worked. The arrests, transportation of suspects, and injured citizens taken to a physician are some of the things recorded. Arranged chronologically.
  - December 4, 1956-January 26, 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 10)
  - March 21, 1957-May 10, 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 10)
  - July 1, 1957-August 18, 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 10)
  - August 19, 1957-October 6, 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 10)
  - January 29, 1958-March 23, 1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 10)
  - March 24, 1958-May 16, 1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 11)
  - May 17, 1958-July 4, 1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 11)
  - August 28, 1958-October 22, 1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 11)
  - December 18, 1958-February 25, 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 11)
  - Febraury 25, 1959-April 30, 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 12)
  - May 1, 1959-June 5, 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 12)
  - July 5, 1959-September 9, 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 12)
  - September 10, 1959-November 16, 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 12)
  - November 17, 1959-January 28, 1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 12)
  - January 29, 1960-April 13, 1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 13)
  - April 14, 1960-June 25, 1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 13)
  - June 25, 1960-August 30, 1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 13)
  - September 5, 1960-November 15, 1960 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 13)
  - November 16, 1960-January 26, 1961 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 13)
  - April 13, 1961-June 21, 1961 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 14)
  - June 22, 1961-September 1, 1961 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 14)
  - November 19, 1961-February 1, 1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 14)
  - February 2, 1962-April 17, 1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 15)
  - April 18, 1962-July 1, 1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 15)
  - July 2, 1962-September 12, 1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 15)
  - September 13, 1962-November 26, 1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 15)
- Complaint Books, 1939-1959; III.
  Records of calls of complaint to the Station #7. Dates, place, and time of incident, how contacted police (telephone, etc.), name and badge number of officer on post at the time of call are given. Fines and/or jail sentence are recorded along with whether the defendant paid the fine. Arranged chronologically.
  - January 1, 1939-May 22, 1946 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 1)
  - April 2, 1951-September 30, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 1)
  - March 12, 1959-December 7, 1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 1)
- Magistrate's Dockets, 1940-1957; IV.
  Records of trials of suspects from Station #7 and Station #9. Most documents only give the name of the defendant, date of hearing, arresting officer's name, and charge. A few record a full statement of the incident along with testimony from the arresting officer and defendant. Most deal with public drunkenness, drunken driving, larceny, burglary, or vagrancy. The sentence, whether jail, a fine, or both, or discharged or committed is recorded. Arranged chronologically.
  Loose miscellaneous materials which were found in the magistrate's dockets. Contain additional testimony. The material was not microfilmed with the magistrates dockets. Arranged chronologically.
  - Station #7 (South Side), 1940-1957; 1.
    - Loose Files
      - 1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
      - 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - 1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - 1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - 1948 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - 1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - 1950 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - 1952 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - 1954 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - 1955 (Box 4, Folder 38-40)
      - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - 1946 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Microfilm
      - March 15, 1940-July 25, 1940 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 2)
      - July 25, 1940-January 8, 1941 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 2)
      - January 9, 1941-June 11, 1941 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 2)
      - June 12, 1941-December 9, 1941 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 3)
      - December 10, 1941-May 2, 1942 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 3)
      - May 3, 1942-September 17, 1942 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 3)
      - March 12, 1943-September 26, 1943 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
      - September 27, 1943-July 19, 1944 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
      - July 20, 1944-June 7, 1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 4)
      - June 7, 1945-March 30, 1946 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
      - March 31, 1946-November 26, 1946 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
      - November 27, 1946-July 15, 1947 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 5)
      - July 16, 1947-February 6, 1948 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
      - February 7, 1948-August 16, 1948 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
      - August 16, 1948-April 13, 1949 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
      - April 14, 1949-December 9, 1949 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 6)
      - December 10, 1949-June 17, 1950 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 7)
      - June 18, 1950-December 29, 1950 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 7)
      - December 30, 1950-August 13, 1951 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 7)
      - August 14, 1957-April 22, 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 7)
      - April 23, 1952-November 10, 1952 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 8)
      - November 12, 1952-June 5, 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 8)
      - June 6, 1953-January 7, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 8)
      - January 7, 1954-September 29, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 9)
      - September 30, 1954-July 2, 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 9)
      - March 4, 1956-January 17, 1957 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 9)
  - Station #9 (Mt. Washington), 1939-1955; 2.
    - October 3, 1939-September 15, 1940 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 16)
    - September 16, 1940-October 26, 1941 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 16)
    - October 27, 1941-October 31, 1942 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 16)
    - November 9, 1942-April 27, 1944 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 17)
    - April 28, 1944-December 23, 1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 17)
    - December 24, 1945-April 2, 1947 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 17)
    - May 24, 1948-August 5, 1949 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 18)
    - August 6, 1949-September 3, 1950 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 18)
    - September 4, 1950-November 4, 1951 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 18)
    - November 6, 1951-January 22, 1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 19)
    - January 23, 1953-April 29, 1954 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 19)
    - April 30, 1954-October 8, 1955 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 2, Reel 19)
- Offense Reports, 1955-1956; V.
  Police Station #7: Reports of crimes committed or attempted with the place, date, time, victim, and valuables stolen or property damaged. The age, sex, race, and occupation of the victim are recorded where applicable. A description of the attack or break-in is given. Descriptions of the property taken or damaged along with its value are recorded. The suspect(s) is/are also described where applicable. Arranged chronologically.
  This is an extension of the Offense Reports. Includes date of the report, date and place of the occurrence, victim's name, home and business address, and additional details. The additional details often discuss the actual investigation of the crime scene. Describes the crime scene and indicates what investigations were performed, e.g., dusting for and finding fingerprints and filing them away for evidence and future reference. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - 1956 (Box 5, Folder 46-47)
  - Supplement to Offense Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 48)
- Juvenile Court Case Referrals [RESTRICTED], 1955-1958; VI.
  Station #7: These are records of crimes committed by or against juveniles. The violations are given, often in detail, and the child's parents' names, address, age, race, sex, and habits at home are recorded. After being arrested, the child is either returned home or taken to a house of detention. Much of the incidents deal with runaways. Arranged chronologically. Restricted access.
  - 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - 1958 (Box 5, Folder 50)
- Juvenile Court Motor Vehicle Violations [RESTRICTED], 1958; VII.
  Station #7: Details violation by the youth(s). Most deal with the individual not having a license, registration, or owner's card. Other incidents are more colorful: one boy was cited for driving too fast through an intersection near a school--he stated he was showing off in front of girls. Another boy was driving too fast for conditions; plus, he had four people in the front seat, five people in the back, and one person hanging on to the side of the car. Arranged chronologically. Restricted access.
  - 1958 (Box 5, Folder 51)
- Officer's Personnel Cards, 1919-1944; VIII.
  These 5" x 8" cards list the officer's name, rank, date and place of birth, social condition; appointment (date) for promotion; former occupation; make of gun, calibre, barrel, and number; language spoken, special qualifications, address, ward, district, and telephone number. On the back is the monthly inspection listing the month, inspecting officer, and equipment inspected. This includes: overcoat, blouse, shirt, hat, trouser, overcoat, gun, mace, nippers, shoes, and appearance. Eleven cards just list name, rank, and shield number. A few cards indicate that the officer joined the Army (during World War II). Arranged alphabetically.
  - Cards, A-W, 1919-1944 (Box 6, Folder 52)
- Employer Reports of Industrial Injury, 1950-1958; IX.
  Records dates and how accident happened, name of officer, date of disability, address, sex, age, years employed, how much money made per day, hours worked per day, number of children under 18, marital status, days worked per week, and the nature and location of the injury (on the person's body). Often included are: detailed reports of the accident and injury, lost time slips, stop salary slips, and resume salary slips--includes occupation and salary per month and year. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Forms, 1950-1958 (Box 6, Folder 53)
- Officer's and Physician's Reports for Motor Vehicle Operators, 1955-1958; X.
  These give accounts of motor vehicle accidents or observations of the arresting officer. The officer takes the individual to a physician who examines the suspect for drugs or alcohol. The date, time, place of violation, name of operator, age, race, sex, occupation, the odor or possession of alcohol are given. A description of the operator's condition of clothes, manner of speech, staggering gait, and conduct: boisterous, unruly, stubborn, disorderly, or quiet are also given. The physician certifies that the operator is/is not drunk. Most of the incidents concern drunken driving. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Forms, 1955-1958 (Box 6, Folder 54)